{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Suspended solid present in the waste water generated in blast furnace gas cooling and cleaning plant is removed by", "opta": "biological oxygen pond.", "optb": "radial settling tank (thickener) using coagulant (lime & ferrous sulphate).", "optc": "lagoons.", "optd": "filtration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Persons working in cement plants and limestone quarries are more prone to disease like", "opta": "cancer", "optb": "asthma", "optc": "silicosis", "optd": "flourosis (bone disease)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Particulates (< 1\u03bcm     size) remaining suspended   in    air   indefinitely   and transported by wind currents are called", "opta": "fumes", "optb": "mists", "optc": "smoke", "optd": "aerosols", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Operating principle of cyclone separator is based on the action of __________ dust particles.", "opta": "diffusion of", "optb": "centrifugal force on", "optc": "gravitational force on", "optd": "electrostatic force on", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exposure to small amount of __________ results in high blood pressure & heart disease in human beings.", "opta": "hydrogen sulphide", "optb": "mercury", "optc": "cadmium", "optd": "asbestos", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum allowable concentration of CO2 in air for safe working is __________ ppm (parts per million).", "opta": "50", "optb": "1000", "optc": "2000", "optd": "5000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tolerable limit of nitrogen oxides in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1", "optc": "5", "optd": "25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron & manganese present as pollutant in water can not be removed by", "opta": "ion exchange process.", "optb": "oxidation followed by settling & filtration.", "optc": "lime soda process or manganese zeolite process.", "optd": "chlorination.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In water chemical treatment plant, use of chloramines ensures", "opta": "disinfection.", "optb": "taste & odour control.", "optc": "weed control in reservoirs.", "optd": "removal of permanent hardness.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the common pollutant emitted from metallurgical smelters, thermal power plant and cement plants ?", "opta": "NOx", "optb": "Hg", "optc": "SO2", "optd": "F", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During which of the following operating conditions of an automobile, carbon monoxide content in the exhaust gas is maximum ?", "opta": "Idle running", "optb": "Acceleration", "optc": "Cruising", "optd": "Deaccelaration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "H2S present in gaseous stream can be removed by adsorption on", "opta": "silica gel", "optb": "active carbon", "optc": "bog iron", "optd": "limestone powder", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inhalation of lead compounds present in automobile exhaust (using leaded petrol) causes", "opta": "blood poisoning.", "optb": "anaemia.", "optc": "nervous system disorder.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Replenishment of dissolved oxygen in water stream polluted with industrial waste occurs by", "opta": "natural aeration of water stream.", "optb": "photosynthetic action of algae.", "optc": "both (a) & (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aerodynamic noise resulting from turbulent gas flow is the most prevalent source of valve noise in fluid ilow control. It is caused due to", "opta": "Reynold stresses", "optb": "shear forces", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke is produced due to", "opta": "insufficient supply of combustion air and insufficient time for combustion.", "optb": "poor quality of fuel and improper mixing of fuel & combustion air.", "optc": "poor design & overloading of furnace.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fluorosis (a bone disease) is caused by the presence of high concentration of __________ in atmospheric air.", "opta": "hydrocarbons", "optb": "hydrogen flouride", "optc": "hydrogen sulphides", "optd": "nitrogen dioxide", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Threshold Limit Value (TLV) is the maximum allowable concentration (i.e. safe limit) of pollutants in air. Safe limit for SO2 in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "5", "optb": "500", "optc": "1000", "optd": "2000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Main pollutants released from iron & steel industry is", "opta": "CO, CO2 & SO2.", "optb": "H2S, NO & SO3.", "optc": "CO2, H2S & NO2.", "optd": "SO3, NO2 & CO2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exposure to chemicals having carcinogenic properties cause", "opta": "dermatitis (skin disorder)", "optb": "cancer", "optc": "asphyxiation (suffocation)", "optd": "asthma", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Scale formation in boiler is controlled by", "opta": "preheating of feed water.", "optb": "reduction in hardness, silica & alumina in feed water.", "optc": "keeping the pH value of feed water just below 7.", "optd": "eliminating H2S in feed water.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise level heard at a distance of about 100 metres from a jet engine with after burner is about __________ decibels.", "opta": "120", "optb": "140", "optc": "170", "optd": "200", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TLV of mercury in potable (drinking) water is about __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.001", "optb": "0.1", "optc": "1", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the best and the most effective method for the removal of organic contaminant present in the polluted water in very small quantity (say < 200 mg/litre)?", "opta": "Lagooning", "optb": "Activated carbon adsorption", "optc": "Biological oxidation pond", "optd": "Chemical coagulation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a secondary air pollutant ?", "opta": "Photochemical smog", "optb": "Sulphur dioxide", "optc": "Nitrogen dioxide", "optd": "Dust particles", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most detrimental for water used in high pressure boiler ?", "opta": "Silica", "optb": "Turbidity", "optc": "Phenol", "optd": "Dissolved oxygen", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Turbidity of water is an indication of the presence of", "opta": "suspended inorganic matter", "optb": "dissolved solids", "optc": "floating solids", "optd": "dissolved gases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of excess flourine in water causes", "opta": "dental cavity", "optb": "tooth decay", "optc": "fluorosis", "optd": "respiratory disease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Siderosis is a disease caused by the inhalation of __________ dust.", "opta": "coal", "optb": "silica", "optc": "iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following pollutants is not emitted during volcanic eruptions ?", "opta": "SO2", "optb": "H2S", "optc": "CO", "optd": "hydrocarbons", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main pollutant in waste water discharged from a petroleum refinery is oil (both in free and emulsified form). Free oil is removed by", "opta": "biological oxygen pond.", "optb": "aerated lagoons.", "optc": "trickling filters.", "optd": "gravity separator having oil skimming devices.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phenolic water generated in coke ovens & by-product plant attached to an integrated steel plant containing phenol in concentration of less than 100 mg/litre can be removed by", "opta": "chlorination", "optb": "treating in biological oxygen pond", "optc": "chemical coagulation", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following dust collection equipments is the least efficient (for sub-micronic particles) ?", "opta": "Dust catcher (gravity type)", "optb": "Cyclone separator", "optc": "Bag filter", "optd": "Hollow wet scrubber", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bag filter design is predominantly dependent on gas temperature, as it affects the gas density & viscosity and the selection of filtering material. The pressure drop in a bag filter is", "opta": "inversely proportional to viscosity of gas.", "optb": "proportional to the viscosity & density of the gas.", "optc": "proportional to the pressure of the gas.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dust collection efficiency of a cyclone separator depends upon its", "opta": "diameter.", "optb": "inlet gas velocity.", "optc": "overall height.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ionisation potential employed in the industrial electrostatic precipitator is of the order of", "opta": "30 to 70 kV DC", "optb": "30 to 70 kV AC", "optc": "230 V AC", "optd": "230 V DC", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The widest explosive limit is of __________ , thereby making it the most explosive gas.", "opta": "acetylene", "optb": "petrol vapor", "optc": "hydrogen", "optd": "carbon monoxide", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aerobic biological oxidation ponds used for the purification of polluted water", "opta": "destroys/removes pathogen from the sewage.", "optb": "is not very effective for nonbiodegradable substances (e.g. ABS) containing effluents.", "optc": "destroys/removes pathogen much more effectively if the sewage is chlorinated.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polluted water having low BOD are most economically treated in", "opta": "sedimentation tanks", "optb": "oxidation ponds", "optc": "sludge digester", "optd": "clarifier", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tri-sodium phosphate is used in boiler water treatment to reduce", "opta": "turbidity", "optb": "caustic embrittlement", "optc": "suspended silica", "optd": "dissolved oxygen", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The commonest form of iron & manganese found in ground water as pollutant is in the form of their", "opta": "carbonates", "optb": "bi-carbonates", "optc": "chlorides", "optd": "sulphides", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "80% less than 200 mesh size particles are called", "opta": "smoke", "optb": "powder", "optc": "grit", "optd": "aggregates", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coal washing waste water containing about 3% suspended solids (comprising of clay, slate, stone etc.) is treated for solid particles removal", "opta": "by chemical coagulation.", "optb": "in sedimentation tanks equipped with mechanical scrapper.", "optc": "in vacuum filter.", "optd": "in clarifiers.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inhalation of lead compounds present in the automobile exhausts (using leaded petrol) causes", "opta": "blood poisoning.", "optb": "anaemia.", "optc": "nervous system disorder.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TLV of ozone (O3) and phosgene (COCl2) in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "25", "optc": "100", "optd": "1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most of the atmospheric air pollutants are present in large quantity in", "opta": "stratosphere", "optb": "thermosphere", "optc": "trophosphere", "optd": "mesosphere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Caustic embrittlement of boiler's metallic parts is caused by high concentration of caustic soda in boiler feed water.", "optb": "Cooling and freezing of water kills the bacteria present in it.", "optc": "With increasing boiler operating pressure of steam, the maximum allowable concentration of silica in feed water goes on decreasing.", "optd": "Dissolved oxygen content in high pressure boiler feed water should be nil.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Pneumoconiosis' is a disease caused by the inhalation of __________ dust.", "opta": "coal", "optb": "uranium ore", "optc": "iron ore", "optd": "lime", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of oxygen available to the oxygen required for stabilisation of sewage is called the", "opta": "bacterial stability factor.", "optb": "relative stability.", "optc": "biological oxygen demand (BOD).", "optd": "oxygen ion concentration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The concentric atmosphere layer just above troposphere is called stratosphere, which is rich in ozone.", "optb": "Mesosphere is characterised by very low atmospheric pressure and low temperature.", "optc": "Troposhere is a dusty zone containing water vapor and clouds.", "optd": "The radio waves used in the long distance radio communication are reflected back to earth by stratosphere.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}